<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Wind In My Hair</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2016-03-15T17:38:01+05:30</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Megha D S</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>dsmegha@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hackathon against Gender Based Violence]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/HackathonAgainstGBV/" />
  <id>/HackathonAgainstGBV</id>
  <published>2016-03-15T00:00:00+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-03-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Megha D S</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>dsmegha@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;A hackathon against Gender Based Violence was organised in Ranchi this January, by the awesome folks at &lt;a href=&quot;https://rhokbangalore.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;RHoK&lt;/a&gt; India and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thebachchaoproject.org/&quot;&gt;Bachchao Project&lt;/a&gt;. I had not attended a Hackathon before, but both Gender Based Equality and Technology being topics close to my heart, I decided to travel to Ranchi for the event. I was able to grab one of the travel and accommodation grants and reached the three day event with great enthusiasm. The event was preceded by a course on Eliademy and discussed various topics like ‘Deconstructing Gender’, ‘Understanding power, discrimination, privilege, and masculinity’ and ‘Women in Public spaces and co-relation to GBV’ were discussed. Participants were asked to discuss their ideas in the open forum and were told about the existing technology initiatives from the around globe and India against GBV. This helped a lot in setting the context and made sure all of us were in the same page at the start of the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first day of the event was the dedicated to interaction between various NGOs and making sure everybody understood the problem we are trying to solve. Personally, I think this was best part of the event. We heard from various NGOs like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yuwa-india.org/&quot;&gt;Yuwa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.swayam.info/&quot;&gt;Swayam&lt;/a&gt; who are working at the ground level to bring about Gender Equality. This interaction provided the much needed perspective for us also. The NGOs, introduced themselves to us and let us know about the problems that they were facing, the solution to which they were hopeful to receive at the Hackathon. There were a lot of technology leaders who could help and mentor us during the event. The participants also had a refresher about the course that they had earlier taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anuradha Kapoor, the Managing Trustee &amp;amp; Founder of Swayam does a lot of advocacy work for her NGO. She needs a lot of data to do this, and in India there is right now a lack of Data. She and her team manually went through various newspapers based out of West Bengal, developing a database of all cases of violence against women reported in the newspaper. They did this effort for six months and had collected some very useful data. However it was too tedious a job to sit and collect news from the papers everyday and she wondered if technology could help her build this database. The answer was yes and projects like this are what make technology interesting to me. I joined a few others who were keen to work on this project, sat with Anuradha to understand the problem better, and by the end of first day, we knew what we would be working on for the next two days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team got together the second day and started working on the project. People kept walking out and new people kept walking in and by the end of the event, I was the only techie working on the project! I will reserve my approach to the solution and the technology details for another blog, but would love to mention the support received by mentors here. They stayed with us through the event making sure we got all the technical help needed, showing us the right direction when we were lost and through regular stand-ups monitored our progress. At the end of the third day, we all showcased our projects and the judges selected the two projects that would go through an accelerator program and receive all the necessary support for the project to go live. Unfortunately mine wasn’t one, but I want to continue working on it and may be help organisations like Swayam one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to mention the attention paid to the logistics of the event. It was perfectly organised, I was picked up from the Railway Station, driven around and dropped off to the airport post the event. The accommodation was perfect and every meal during the stay was taken care. It was one of the best events I attended, my first technology event and I learnt a lot. Thanks a lot for arranging this, Bachchao and RHoK.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/HackathonAgainstGBV/&quot;&gt;Hackathon against Gender Based Violence&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Megha D S at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Wind In My Hair&lt;/a&gt; on March 15, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remote jobs with Toptal]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/toptal-application/" />
  <id>/toptal-application</id>
  <published>2015-08-11T00:00:00+05:30</published>
  <updated>2015-08-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Megha D S</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>dsmegha@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;It was July 2013. By then, I had been working in the software industry for networking giants like Cisco and Juniper for almost four years. It was a great job, many people’s dream job. I wrote some good code and earned good money. But there was something missing. I loved my job, but at the end of the day I still felt dissatisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first tryst with the mountains had been made much earlier, when I cycled 550 km from the sleepy town of Kullu in Himachal Pradesh to Leh, the capital of Ladakh. This nineteen day affair included passing through several high altitude passes and even cycling on the highest motor-able road in the world. I had fallen in love with the Mountains. I promised myself I will be back to the mountains at least once an year. This time, I went ahead with a two week trip to the remote valleys of Lahaul and Spiti, Himachal Pradesh. The trip was not life changing, but it gave me a lot of time to think about what I want and where I want my career to head. By the time I was back in Bangalore, India’s silicon valley certain things were clear. I had got to know myself better - I did not enjoy being in crowded places, I did not enjoy living in the concrete jungles that the metros are, I did not think it was great to buy a posh house and spend the rest of the life paying the EMIs. I did not want to get back to the software job I had. Don’t get me wrong, I still loved writing software. It was one of the things I enjoyed and was good at, but just loving the job wasn’t enough. I realized that the everyday commute would drain me out. I still remember getting into the city traffic the first day after I got back from my trip and thinking life cannot be just this. I would spend about an hour and a half to get to office everyday. That meant I was spending fifteen hours a week just for getting to office and back. I could rent a place nearby to reduce the commute time, but that would mean I was living in a ‘not so great’ locality, and my social life would get affected. Being born and brought up in Mysore, a quiet town, I was longing to get back my hometown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally quit my job at Juniper networks in November 2013 and moved back to my hometown. I joined a travel startup, goMowgli travels and traveled for the next year in Karnataka, Kerala and Goa. I was the product head in my company, which meant I had the responsibility of coming up with the entire product. This included deciding what places our company would take the customers to, what off-beat experiences we recommend them to try, which accommodations give the most satisfying stay options. We built partnerships with activity and accommodation providers. At the end of my tenure, I had built a solid product for the company. I had also got back to the mountainspa a lot more. The most memorable one was the chadar trek, walking on a frozen river in extreme cold. I also completed my Basic Mountaineering Course from Nehru Institute of Mountaineering, one of the most prestigious Mountaineering institutes in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrap up my work with goMowgli, I have a question in my mind, what next? I know deep down, that I want to get back to software and work on some great products. But I am also sure I do not want to move back to the chaos that Bangalore is. And that’s when it all fell into place. Remote jobs. I could get to work on the most challenging technologies, from the comforts of my home. I could travel as I want, spend six months in the Alps and another six in South Africa, still doing what I love, writing some good code. Toptal offers just that, remote jobs that provide me with challenging work and the flexibility that does not tie me to a 9-5 office desk job. It helps me find a good job and ensure my skills are being utilized at the right place. It selects only the best, making sure I am in elite company. It is the perfect solution for people like me and I am hoping for some great years at toptal.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/toptal-application/&quot;&gt;Remote jobs with Toptal&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Megha D S at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Wind In My Hair&lt;/a&gt; on August 11, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
